the different reasons that people will
be meditating for but based on the sort
of meditation should be developed should
help develop understanding it's not
about switching things off and absorbing
yourself in some states whereby nothing
else will be it will be present in
awareness it's really about surmounting
the states Sumati the unwholesome states
amount in the states that cause us to
suffer for understanding them so so
really practicing meditation should be
practice of of developing in mind
finding a place in your mind then you
can maintain throughout the day even
when you're not actively meditating so
for example and that's why in another
another talks you would often say that
guided meditation guiding contemplation
we would use it interchangeably because
it is it is it's pretty much a right
type of contemplation that then results
in certain in that ability of your mind
and in that way it's a it's a meditation
so for example we can like now we can we
can you can contemplate pick up a state
that bothers you throughout the day or
or causes you issues whatever that is
and then you can you can reflect on it
and learn how to discern it rightly so
like you can you can imagine example the
anger let's say anger that can be our
example here
so that can be your meditation you can
set some quiet time inside prevent any
any any disturbances half an hour
whatever whatever you can do
and then actively think upon the present
experience without losing the sight of
that present experience so you want to
know how to you learn how to think
without greed aversion delusion so the
phenomenon of anger you don't have to be
angry to when you when you when you want
to do this meditation but just bring it
to the forum remember when you are angry
so you're investigating the phenomenon
of anger the phenomenon of gijón well so
you don't want to be trying to get rid
of it or imagine the state whereby it
will never arise you want to be you
won't understand it you want to see to
what extent that which makes you angry
is inevitable and then to what extent
there is your responsibility in regard
to it so in terms of anger
just imagine the times when you were
angry and you can let it in do let it be
present for a while don't over thinking
but don't over think it but certainly
don't don't try to no thinking either
so you can ask yourself but for example
imagine when you were angry then you can
imagine many other times if you were
angry or irritated if you're not getting
angry maybe irritated or annoyed what is
in common to all of those experiences of
anger or vegetation what is what is a
common thread that unites them or what
is the nature so you can answer this
question in many ways and it so crucial
to always answer the answer in the same
way because really you're not University
80 so sometimes you your investigation
will lead you to different aspects of it
of phenomenon but just keep pressing
with the questions while the phenomenon
is enduring so the phenomenon of anger
all the times I was angry irritated
annoyed what is in common to all of
those experiences
see what you come up with
one of the most obvious things that is
in common is it's unpleasant every
single time you experience anger it's
unpleasant that experience is not nice
so then you can ask the second question
can you be angry without the little
sting of displeasure is there any anger
that is truly truly enjoyable and
pleasant experience of anger now you
might have like a secondary experience
of pleasure but getting revenge or
getting back at someone through anger
and then you get that satisfaction but
that's not what we are talking about
talking about the actual the very first
originally enduring phenomenon of anger
is that Pleasant or unpleasant it's
always unpleasant
there is no single exception because if
you weren't unpleasant say something
tell others somebody does something that
upsets you they'll teach you so that's
that's that's your anger you really
teach it you got angry because you are
upset for whatever reason now say no on
other occasion you're in a good mood and
somebody does the same thing to you but
now you really did not experience that
stink of discomfort through that upset
and you're not angry you might even
laugh it off so you realize it anger
then it's not determined directly
determined but what's done to you it's
really determined whether by its really
determined by whether you're
experiencing discomfort on account of
what's done to you
so it's really the discomfort coming in
contact having discomfort arise in your
experience that's where your anger is
rooted in it's not rooted in
circumstances that bring that anger
forward so every time you are angry
irritated I know it means to some degree
you're upset doesn't matter how hard I
find that upset might be it's still the
upset which means there is a degree of
discomfort displeasure unpleasant
feeling every single time and every
single time you will get upset in the
future there will be the common thread
today really when you're getting angry
over in the present will you be getting
over get angry over in the past or you
will getting lower in the future it's
it's you being liable to discomfort on
the emotional level so you experiencing
unpleasant feelings is what makes you
angry and don't try now like jump and
look into immediate solution how do I
stop doing this because it's not on the
level of doing as you will be performing
any other action it's subtler than that
you stop doing it
by understanding it so you stop doing it
by ceasing to act out of ignorance of it
those are the way to stop doing it so
how'd you stop acting out of ignorance
of your anger well you stop ignoring the
true nature of anger
you learn how to maintain the
mindfulness of it art allow it to endure
and you're tellin it you actively make
the effort as reset let me start it is
to think it concretely thinking properly
in the present moment not ignore it not
justified now provide a random set is
emotionally satisfying answers to it so
by dwelling on the nature of anger
clarifying it further and further and
further I'm doing all the layers of
ignoring that you developed through
blindly imminently acting out of anger
all this time in my job all this what
you described means the same principle
that sensuality lost there is anything
unwholesome so you have to restrain
yourself first you're angry
don't give in to anger we have been
giving in to anger then you can started
collecting on the nature of anger
correctly like what you just what we
just done so every time you rang every
time there was an anger in your
experience it was rooted in discomfort
so can they be pressed further can you
best take it further what is in common
every single discomfort which you ever
experienced what kind of attitude was in the
what kind of attitude was in the
background of it
your attitude every time you encountered
unpleasant feeling for a prospect of an
unpleasant feeling what was the what was
the background of it but what was the
common thread to all this different
phenomena of unpleasant experiences
in the past in the future doesn't matter
how many I'll feel if any phenomena of
unpleasant nature has arisen
you must have taken in a certain nature
of being unpleasant so what is that
nature practically speaking no
theoretically practically speaking what
is in common to every displeasure you
ever went through in your book and you
will ever go through
it's not wanted isn't it
every time there's a genuinely
emotionally experience discomfort it's
not wanted that's what's in common you
resist it you want it to not be there
you feel entitled to wanting it to not
be there
so every time you were angry means every
one every every of those time you were
experiencing a form of discomfort every
time there's a form of discomfort every
time there's a form of unpleasant
feeling every time there is a resistance
to it so then you can safely assume that
whenever there is an anger experience of
anger there is resistance to it you
trying to get rid of it my set
why you try get who why is that and what
are you trying to get rid of it what
exactly should not be there from that
point of view is it circumstances
they're upset they're upset does that
caused us that discomfort or the
discomfort itself
what is your cranium trying to get rid
of
it's always a discomfort even if if you
are aiming in the circumstances you do
so so to remove the basis for that
displeasure that you have being touched
by so what if theoretically speaking now
you can imagine to not resist the
displeasure to stop resisting it so no
like battle the circumstances defend
attack prevent but just internally
whenever there is a discomfort you're
mindful of it and make sure there is no
giving in to the attitude of I don't
want this doesn't mean you want it but
means you stopped not wanting it
that's the subtlety of the middle way
opposite of wanting of opposite of not
wanting is not wanting sorry let's below
this wanting is not the opposite of not
wanting phenomena logically speaking
will be very accurate which you must
opposite of not wanting is the absence
of not wanting it's not the presence of
wanting so in other words when there is
resistance
- unpleasant feeling doesn't mean now
you must learn how to want the
unpleasant feeling in order to get rid
of the resistance it only means you need
to stop resisting it you don't need to
overdo it and going the other way that's
why when when when the Buddha said he
crossed the show by not pushing forward
by not pulling backwards by not standing
still when they said well how did you do
that he said well I didn't push forward
by not pushing forward
I didn't pulled backwards by not pulling
backwards he didn't say I didn't pull
backwards by pushing forward so the
absence of pulling backwards is how you
stop pulling backwards the absence of
resisting the unpleasant feeling is how
you stop resisting it so when people say
hate is only conquered by love that's
not true absolutely
hey is conquered by non hate love is
conquered by non love so you don't be
swinging from one end to the other or
other you won't you won't be able to
help but initially but if you start
discerning bit if you learn how to not
resist anger that doesn't mean you must
love the circumstances they caused it -
or or anything like it you just need to
stop resisting it and you will stop
resisting it when you truly understand
the nature of unpleasant feeling so
let's get back to the practical side of
it as we've been discussing it remember
all the times you're angry again bring
it back we drifted away bring it back so
every single time you were irritated
annoyed angry upset every one of those
times it was unpleasant
so being irritated angular upset means
being exposed to displeasure enduring it
being touched by it
sucio we already to degree transcended
one beyond the particular circumstances
did might have made you angry or upset
we said what what happened to you all
that it's really secondary you are angry
now because there is this pleasure
present you are angry because the
present displeasure is not wanted you
take that for granted then your actions
angry actions will be coming out of it
so anger is fen logically secondary to
your resistance to displeasure anger is
your reaction to your own resistance
basically you resist the discomfort and
that in itself it's quite uncomfortable
so then you a denial another layer of
then trying to get rid of your attempts
of getting rid of the unpleasant feeling
so as I said what if you just stop
resisting the unpleasant feeling
just a degree you've been resisting and
you stopped resisting it just to degree
that there is the attitude of this is
not wanted to that degree you remove
that attitude so you can't do that
intentionally as and you can't decide
make a decision ah stop resisting it
because if that happens to proceed your
intentions are result of that attitude
that's why the world would say you he
avoids the intent acting upon intentions
that are rooted in unwholesome when he
acts upon intentionally holes also his
absence of a virgin so you will stop
maintaining that attitude when you fully
this that in regard to which your
attitude is maintained unpleasant
feeling so we imagine times we were
angry they may see what what what the
common thread in that is it's the
discomfort see what the common thread in
every single discomfort is it's the
unpleasant it's the resisting of that
unpleasant feeling so this is again this
is not like something that will lead us
to some sort of great of the what we
might lead you to some grand conclusions
but it's more like the value of this is
in being repetitively done this self
questioning and the reflection
contemplation meditation so that's a
woman he keeps reviewing his mind to
create a version delusion it's all you
do once you provide the answers in
that's it you've done no can you do it
again and certainly you do it when with
the context that you have developed to
providing these answers ceases when you
can't go distract from it and so on you
did do it
now you might arrive with different
contexts but the point is you keep doing
it because you're doing it you're
removing this your own layers of
ignoring it of being unfamiliar with it
so one of the main things that everyone
well the the undeveloped mind minds are
unfamiliar with is the nature of the
unpleasant feeling so we were looking at
the nature of anger
brought us to the world nature
discomfort they brought us to the nature
resisting the discomfort so you can now
you could even say what is the nature
resistance then attitude of resistance
craving for things to not be what is in
common to every single one of those it's
in common that they're bound up with
every single time you experienced
unpleasant feeling so that begs the
question then can you speed in some
present feeling without trying to get
rid of it and that's pretty much your
first step towards practical application
of this very contemplation so you using
your sitting quietly method and Lettuce
contemplating but now when you go back
to the world when unpleasantness touches
you and inevitably will you remember to
try what you've been discerning what if
I stop resisting this that's not not the
circumstances like I'm restrained in
regards of circumstances but they were
never the problem he said this so that
that's not the problem is that the
discomfort touches me and automatically
upon being touched i simul taneous we
don't want that why is that why do I
maintain the view that I have that I'm
in a position to prevent feelings for
manifesting and that's the thing that we
arrived at now can you could you be
resisting anything if that thing hasn't
arisen beforehand and i said beforehand
i mean right there at the same time but
before your attitude or rather more
fundamental to your attitude the basis
for your attitude
so united to the resisting displeasure
is simultaneous to displeasure but
displeasure is first in that structure
of phenomenological manner so would you
be able to be resisting any feeling if
that feeling is not there on its own
manifested for you to resist it
to bring it to my anytime experience any
form of discomfort emotional my given
now just abstractly you think about
world pain and it already has a
significance implied in place its
significance of not wanted to be
prevented
so can you stop that can you not go in
one pane can you just stop
not wanting of it can you be indifferent
to it that's basically what we are
saying and the good news is you can if
you understand the nature of it did you
have any say in its arising if so why
did it then arise in the first place
when it's not wanted from the start so
you didn't really because if you did it
wouldn't have a reason so unpleasant
feelings then arrives on their own is
that a problem because it's we give the
example and we started this many
occasions the same things that sometimes
make you suffer arise and then but you
don't feel unpleasant on account to them
so those things they cause that
seemingly cause that displeasure and not
always unpleasant which means sometimes
there might be sometimes we may not be
but so then only their only problem
they're only the problem when they are
present
which means then the problem is not the
things they caused your displeasure the
problem is the displeasure and
especially doesn't always arise but when
it does it's a problem because the
rights to the trying to get rid of it
so would you be able to maintain the
attitude try to get rid of displeasure
if you're not holding on to view that
you can get rid of that displeasure
if you if you truly completely realize
the domain of displeasure oppression the
main feeling is inaccessible to you
would you still be acting as if you have
access to it would you even entertain
such notions in your thoughts
so the feelings when a counterweight you
have attitude of wanting them not
wanting them and so on
you have no say in their arising you
have no say whatsoever so why do you
then maintain the attitude as if you do
have a say because you as we just
clarified discovered you wouldn't be
trying to get rid of the did unpleasant
feeling unless there is an implicit
assumption that you can get rid of it
but when you look at your pleasant
feeling you realize it has a reason on
its own fully enclosed independent of
you and you are not saying it all all
you can do is secondarily complain about
it try to get a little bit prevent it
affect the circumstances they did have
kind of indirectly propped it up so why
do them still hold on to the attitude of
not wanting of trying to get rid of it
craving for it to not be
see here now the mind would expect some
direct answer
they will undo this thing all together
right away by the actual answer I mean
it can be a direct answer but the well
that also tell you is that it's not
because you're making some sort of a
mistake once and then you provide an answer and
once and then you provide an answer and
the mistake is removed and you never
ever come back to it it's because of
your other underlying attitude there is
even more fundamental attitude to the
attitude of craving for getting rid of
the unpleasant feeling and that attitude
is the attitude of ignorance attitude of
ignoring the nature of the feeling
pleasant or unpleasant in neutral that's
what ignorance is the most fundamental
existential error for which every single
human being is responsible but every
single thing is responsible so it's
through ignoring the nature of feeling
nature of as we describe the nature of
it to be arising on its own manifest the
to you for you but you are not its
creator you have no say in the way of
these feelings where they come from
you're just subjected to them in the
same sense the earth is subjected to
weather you just can't even conceive preventing
you just can't even conceive preventing
feelings from being there not dwelling
on that very nature long enough that's
how you maintain the fully gratuitous
attitude of resisting feelings or
indulging feelings because any attitude
towards feeling in twice as we said the
assumption that you can affect those
feelings I mr. prolonging them were
getting rid of them but you realize the
weather you're prolonging trying to
prolong them or get rid of them dead
secondary to the present enduring
feeling that has a reason on its own if
you stop ignoring that these attitudes
will fade
that's why ignorant cannot be undone
accidentally you cannot accidentally stumble upon the
you cannot accidentally stumble upon the
answer of the universe they will solve
and prevent you from suffering ever
again because it wasn't it's not a mistake
because it wasn't it's not a mistake
it's an attitude that you maintain
through your attitude so a visa is the
cause for more of each ignoring is the
reason that there is ignoring attitude
of ignoring ignoring what ignoring the
most fundamental present right in your
face nature of the five aggregates the most
nature of the five aggregates the most
fundamental nature of the feeling not
dwelling on it long enough
oh no dwelling on it at all you can see
what are different this approaches this
approach to it meditation is then well
you'll be commonly commonly doing when
you practicing focusing or concentration
through some technique but then you can
also see which one of the two methods
were more likely a result in your
cessation active ignoring so ceasing of
your active ignoring of certain truths
they were right in front of it and you
can also see cannot be given to you
somebody cannot do that for you make you
stop ignoring the nature of the feeling
that's present in your experience right
here right now the most another person
can do is talk about it rightly
they will then make you make the right
effort right effort being recognized in
the nature of the feeling for example
the nature of unpleasant feeling and see
it as an independently arisen presently
enduring phenomena that even if you
resist that is secondary to it you have
no say in it that's so you stop
resisting unpleasant feeling for example
not by deciding to not resist
the unpleasant feeling but by fully
overriding it with the understanding
that whether you resist or not makes no
difference resisting is futile that's how resisting
resisting is futile that's how resisting
fate
so see seem to ignore the obvious
futility of your resistance to your
emotionally emotional presence mm
present emotional state so that's how
you stop resisting it understanding the
1580 of it but seeing it while the
presently enduring unpleasant feeling is
there not just thinking about it
abstractly and if you do sort of fall
into abstraction you go back to concrete
thinking because there is always a
feeling right here right now that's the
previous stokes we done like when you
when you ask yourself but now you might
have drifted away with all this
information but you ask yourself okay so
so what am I feeling right here right
now overall and the most fundamental
level that I could be aware of they the
most general background in your mind but
what what basis of feeling is there am i
okay am i not okay neither training does
answer is the right answer if that's how
you feel at a time so you recognize that
that basis is is something that is not
your doing that basis is something that
it's there whether you want it to be or
not so not ignoring trying to spend as
much time as possible so it's dwelling
on the nature of that basis nature of it
being independent of you being
indifferent to you that's how you stop
maintaining all these gratuitous
attitudes towards it attitudes that
imply ownership control entitlement yes
you have a right for this to not be
there your right foot is too long to
stay longer and so on so those attitudes
are simply rooted in you ignoring the
nature of things in regard to which
those attitudes are being exercised
so you're trying like imagine you're
trying to break through a door you will
keep trying for as long as there is a
hope that you can do it and then
suddenly you hear the possibility that
maybe maybe there's no need to be
breaking through this door there's no
need to get rid of it and then you
understand that truly there is no need
notice that you understand it you can't
even if you want there's no door
actually it's fully cemented concreted
metal block painting is a door inviting
it to try and break it that's basically
where the feelings are they they present
themselves as if they are for you which
is why the attitude of ignoring that
they have a reason on its own for you
that's why they're actually is developed
that's where ignorance is beginningless
things do deceive you in your sense of
ownership because that's nothing other
than sense of ownership you trying to
get rid of that which has a reason on
its own means you assuming the ownership
and the right to have it disappear or
stay longer like you you act as if
you're its master and controller that's
inherently the conceit I am and sense of
self so things deceive you into that
they present themselves as if well they
presenters are there for you and because
of that you assume that you are that you
are truly because I am but I am Who I am
because see all these things that are
mine all these things at them for me
when I solve these things I mean even
the phenomenon of your perception and
your feeling so feeling present
themselves as if they are controllable
and that's why you just swapped into
that trap of trying to control them
and that's why you suffer as the Buddha
himself said you don't suffer because
there is displeasure present when you
don't suffer because misfortune happens
to you and so on you suffer because
there is craving present in regard to
the present feeling so presence of
craving means presence of suffering in
regard to the feeling not presence of
feeling means presence of suffering
absence of craving means assets of
suffering so you remove yoga traders
attitude attitude there was the truth as
right from the start but because you
were ignoring the basis in regard to it
you're exercising that attitude you were
not clear you were muddled about the
nature of your feeling that's why you
maintain the gradually assumed as usual
that these feelings are for you because
of that you will be trying to get rid of
the displeasure and trying to to indulge
and prolong the pleasure and be
completely distracted model deluded in
regard to the neither pleasure nor
displeasure but by not ignoring it you
stop providing the basis for these
attitudes and eventually they will have
to fade because then require maintenance
maintenance of of ignorance
so that's how you learn to think rightly
as well correctly as the good to call
you the master of his thought person who
does this he won't be thinking anything
out of greed aversion anything out of
indulging or trying to get rid of things
anything are delusional ignoring because
he is stopped ignoring the fundamental
nature of his experience the fundamental
nature of the five aggregates ceasing to
ignore the nature of fire hydrates
ceases to fuel the fire of assumption
even death burns up completely gone
what's left there is just the aggregates
that have been freed from any
assumptions and these are exactly
assumptions you assume at face value
that the feeling can be changed and see
you have the unpleasant feeling then you
make all these after actions chase the
experiences they will provide you with
the pleasant feeling that's a separate
experience now you haven't dealt with
originally unpleasant feeling it ceased
on its own and now you're experiencing
some other pleasure on account of your
test productions they've been chasing it
but even that feeling of that pleasure
has a reason on its own in other words
it's not a guarantee did the actions
towards the world will result in it
always the same type of feeling and
that's enough to then reveal the nature
of of its independence of you and that's
why the Buddha said if a teacher doesn't
doesn't know any other escape from the
reason unpleasant feeling except
sensuality as in replacing it with
another experience of pleasant feeling
not dealing with it with the fundamental
nature of being affected by this
pleasure but if you're not affected if
you cease to be affected by a pleasant
feeling if you cease to resist it in
that ignorant manner why would you be
needing to replace it with any other
feeling that you wouldn't that's why for
somebody who is free from a version
he becomes free from sensuality as well
hand in hand free from sensuality is
free from aversion it's pretty much the
state of Aragon
this ceasing to ignore the fundamental
nature of the present enduring feeling
whatever the feeling is pleasant
unpleasant a neutral and you can see it
ignore when you begin to learn what you
have been ignoring not ignoring the
natural feeling doesn't mean like you
were super aware of feeling
disappearance of illness every secondary
experience means the attitude of being
muddled unclear unfamiliar with its
nature has been abandoned how do you
abandon the attitude of that but
becoming familiar by developing clarity
in regard to it how do you become
familiar and develop clarity by making
the effort to do so by bringing it to
your mind don't let yourself get not let
no letting yourself get distracted and
dwelling it's well on its nature
obviously the guidance of suitors and
Dhamma talks and so on gives you
pointers way to look for but you must be
making an effort to look for it because
not looking for it means automatically
ignoring it and it's not about chasing
particular feelings of particular issues
that might bother you as we started this
whole thing
it's basically stepping back going
developing that peripheral vision they
will they will reveal the nature of any
of those particular things so that when
we started this by saying whenever you
were angry or annoyed or whatever else
what was a common thread through all of
those experiences it was that they're
unpleasant what is the common thread to
all the unpleasant experiences not
necessarily just anger something well
the common thread is that you resist it
there is no unpleasant experience it
doesn't have simultaneously present
resistance in regard to it unless of
course you already know that
so then anytime any particular thing
touched you in an unpleasant way
emotionally means there was resistance
to that so you have two options here try
and control manipulate prevent the world
or simply remove get you the resistance
in regard to anything that can touch you
and only one of these hedges will result
in freedom from suffering